王国福音伝道者のための学校に
申し込んで
Have you applied
to the School for Kingdom Evangelizers
but not been invited?
招待を待っていますか
Or have you wanted to apply
いつ申し込んだらよいか
but wondered if the time was right?
迷っておられるでしょうか
You are not alone.
そういう方も多くいます
Because of the pandemic,
classes are still suspended.
コロナ禍のため 現在クラスは
開かれていません
But if you are a pioneer
between the ages of 23 and 65
でも 23歳から65歳の開拓者で
and would like to attend
a future class of SKE,
SKEの将来のクラスへの
出席を望む方は
please contact your congregation secretary
どうぞ会衆の書記に連絡し
and fill out the online application
オンラインで申し込みをしてください
so that it can be considered
when classes resume.
クラスが再開される時に考慮されます
As a reminder, your application
is active for one year.
ご存じの通り 申込書は1年間有効です
Therefore, you must apply each year
that you desire to be considered.
それで SKEの申込書は
毎年提出してください
Additionally, we are pleased to inform you
なお 宣教訓練学校や
独身の兄弟のための聖書学校を卒業し
that graduates
of the Ministerial Training School
or the Bible School for Single Brothers
現在も独身で全時間奉仕を
行っている方も
who are still single and in full-time service
王国福音伝道者のための学校に
申し込めることをお知らせいたします
may now apply
for the School for Kingdom Evangelizers.
厳しい試練や圧力に遭う時にも
Is it possible to maintain our peace
when dealing with intense trials
and pressures?
平和を保つことはできるでしょうか
How does Jehovah care for our needs
when we are in distress?
困難な時に エホバはどのように
世話してくださるでしょうか
次の動画で エホバから
The following video will introduce us
to brothers and sisters
平和を与えられている兄弟姉妹の
経験を見ることができます
who have been blessed by Jehovah
with peace.
The title is
主題は 「平和な心を
持ち続けている兄弟姉妹
How Our Brothers Are Enjoying Peace
Despite . . . Opposition, Illness,
反対 病気 失業 災害」です
Economic Problems, Natural Disasters.
サタンが支配する世界で生活する限り
As long as we live in Satan’s world,
私たちは誰もが平和を失いかねない
状況に直面します
all of us will face situations
that can rob us of our peace.
平和を取り戻すのは
簡単ではありませんが
Regaining that peace can be difficult
but not impossible.
不可能ではありません
In this video, we will hear
この動画では 3人の姉妹と
2組の夫婦が
from three sisters and two couples
どんな試練に直面し
who will speak candidly about their trials
どのように対処したか
and how they struggled to cope with them.
ありのままに話してくれます
兄弟姉妹は大変な経験をしている中でも
But in spite of what they have endured,
笑顔と喜びを失ってはいません
please take note of their smiles, their joy,
平和な気持ちを取り戻し
キープするために
and what they did to regain
and maintain their peace.
何を行っているでしょうか
And take special note
of how Jehovah helped them.
エホバがどのように助けているかにも
特に注目しましょう
統治体は 皆さんの多くが
The Governing Body knows that many of you
これから紹介する兄弟姉妹と
are suffering circumstances
似たような状況にある
ということを知っています
not unlike the ones we will hear about,
and they trust that the examples
in this video
皆さんがさまざまな試練に耐えながらも
平和な気持ちを持ち続ける上で
will help each of you to maintain your peace
この動画の経験が役立つと信じています
as you endure various trials.
Brothers and sisters all over the world
are facing
世界中の兄弟姉妹たちが
natural disasters,
自然災害
economic collapse,
経済的な問題
illness,
病気
迫害を経験しています
and persecution.
そんな中でも
Despite all that,
喜びや平和を失ってはいません
they keep joy and peace.
兄弟たちからたくさんのことを学べます
I can learn a lot from them.
My name is Antoinette.
私はアントワネットです
I live here in Las Vegas, Nevada,
ネバダ州ラスベガスに 元気なママと
やんちゃな妹と一緒に住んでいます
with my supermom
and my troublemaking sister.
家族や友達のことを
ずっと大切にしてきました
Family and friends have always been
important to me.
As a child, I lived with my mom and dad
子供の頃は両親と一緒に住んでいて
and I was very close
to my dad’s side of the family.
父の親族とも仲良くしていました
優しくって うん 一緒にいて
すごく楽しかったです
It was very loving, unified, and fun.
とっても幸せでした
I was pretty happy.
その時すでにがんの影響が
出始めていましたが
But I already was starting to feel
the effects of my cancer.
当時はまだ理由が分かりませんでした
We just didn’t know what it was really.
大丈夫な日もあるのに 次の日には
具合が悪くなるっていう感じでした
One day I was OK, and then the next day
I started feeling bad, you know.
In my childhood,
子供の頃
ちょっと変わった遊びをしていました
I played an unusual game.
I would catch insects,
虫を捕まえて
put them in a jar, and then bring them home.
瓶に入れ 家に持ち帰っていました
そして 本を取り出し
Then, I would get books,
such as the Criminal Procedural Code,
法律の本なんですけど 開いて
open them up,
and start judging one of the bugs.
虫たちの裁判をしていました
検察官と裁判官の
両方の役をやっていました
I would play the role
of investigator and judge at the same time.
私が生まれた家は
I was born into a family where everyone,
祖父母の頃から
starting with my grandparents,
みんな警察官だったり
裁判官だったりしました
was either wearing an officer’s uniform
or a judge’s robe.
That’s why I had
this strong sense of justice.
だから すごく強い正義感を
持っていました
But in 1989,
でも1989年に
my mother was in a tragic car accident,
母が悲惨な交通事故に遭い
and
顔と手と体に
she got severe burns
on her face, hands, and body.
ひどいやけどを負ってしまいました
And then my father,
父は母の状態を見て
at seeing my mom’s condition,
decided to leave us.
私たちの元を去りました
うん
Yeah.
And it was at that moment, I guess,
今から思うと その時に
that my world, my ideals,
私の世界や理想が
崩れたんでしょうね
they crumbled.
As a little kid, I always wanted, like,
one big happy family.
小さい頃は 親戚みんなが
近くにいたので楽しかったです
治療のためにニューヨークに
移ってからは
Once we moved to New York for my treatment,
親戚とのつながりが
なくなってしまいました
I no longer had that big family bond anymore.
What I was feeling back then in New York was
ニューヨークにいた頃は 悲しくて
just sadness,
全然平和な気持ちではありませんでした
never really peace.
Here in California,
カリフォルニアでは
山火事がよくあります
we’re used to fires.
その日の朝 逃げるように
という電話が来た時
But when I got the call to evacuate
that morning,
その日のうちに このパラダイスという
町がなくなるとは思いませんでした
I never knew that by that evening,
the whole town of Paradise would be gone.
ちょうど火事が起きる前の会衆の必要で
Just before the fire,
we had the needs of the congregation
災害の時どうするかの
指示が扱われました
where they instructed us
what to do in the case of a disaster.
I had the truck full of gas,
ガソリンは満タンにしてありましたし
I had my go bag ready,
非常用持ち出し袋と
行く先の地図を持って
出ることができました
and I had a map of where I was going.
準備はできていました
I was ready.
会衆の必要で兄弟たちが
The brothers, also in their instructions,
交通規制に従うようにとも
言っていました
said to obey the traffic instructors.
The instructor told us to turn right,
道で右に曲がるようにと言われましたが
行きたくありませんでした
and I didn’t want to turn right,
but they said obey them.
でも従うようにと言われていたので
右に曲がりました
So I turned right,
絶対こっちじゃないと
思ったんですけどね
though I thought it would be really bad.
煙がどんどん濃くなっていきました
The smoke got darker and darker,
ついには真っ暗になりました
and finally it got black.
何にも見えませんでした
You couldn’t see anything.
My mom has always told me
母から 私は小さい頃から
面倒見のいい子だと言われてきました
that I’ve always been
a caregiver ever since I was a little girl;
it was just part of who I was.
人のお世話が好きだから
自然とできちゃうんです
苦しんでいる人を見ると
とてもつらくなります
I don’t like to see people suffer;
it’s very difficult for me.
今思えば 看護師として働き始めた頃
I remember that when I first started working
as a nurse,
いつも泣いていました
I would always cry.
I cried—
Literally I cried
仕事に行くのが嫌で
ほんとに毎日泣いていました
every day that I had to go to work.
新人ナースで やる事に追われて
いっぱいいっぱいだったのに加えて
Not only was I overwhelmed
being a new nurse
but also
うん 鬱でもあったので 大変でした
I was battling my depression.
2017年 私はニカラグアの大手の
銀行で財務管理の仕事をしていました
In 2017,
I was the treasurer
for a prestigious bank in Nicaragua,
息子が生まれて1歳になり
and I was the father of a one-year-old son.
とても幸せに暮らしていました
We were very happy.
でもその後 失業してしまいました
But then I lost my job.
その時 こう思いました
So I said, ‘I have the experience,
「自分には経験があるし
and Jehovah will help me find another job,
something similar.’
エホバは似たような別の仕事を
見つけられるようにしてくれるだろう」
ずっと仕事を探していましたが
見つかりませんでした
And I kept looking for jobs,
but doors kept closing.
とてもストレスを感じました
I felt very tense;
家族を養うこともできないのかと思うと
it made me feel very useless,
like
本当に情けなくなりました
I couldn’t even provide for my family.
とても苦しく つらい時期でした
It was something very difficult for me.
These dear brothers and sisters
これらの兄弟姉妹たちは
とても難しい問題にぶつかりました
faced serious challenges.
ヨブのように感じることも
あったでしょう
They may have had moments
when they felt like Job
ヨブは 「私は自分の命に
嫌気が差します」と言いました
when he said: “I loathe my life.”
That is not an unusual human emotion.
そう感じるのも
おかしいことではありません
Sometimes things in life
時には思いも寄らないような
問題を経験し
don’t work out as we had hoped,
打ちのめされてしまうことも
あるでしょう
and it can hurt us deeply.
そうなってしまうと なすすべがなく
Does this mean that we are helpless victims
of our circumstances?
絶望するしかないのでしょうか
そんなことはありません
Not at all!
Please pay close attention
動画の続きをご覧になり
絶望的な状況でも
and take note of why we can say
マーガレット フェリクス ミゲル
ニッキー アントワネットが
that Margaret, Feliks,
Miguel, Nikki, and Antoinette
穏やかな気持ちを失わなかったことに
注目してください
are not helpless victims.
To the contrary,
この5人は負けませんでした
they are conquerors.
As you watch and listen,
5人の兄弟姉妹はそれぞれ
look for specific actions they took
どのようにして平和な心を
持ち続けたかを話してくれます
to maintain their peace
そしてぜひ 私たちがその信仰に
どのように倣えるかを考えてみましょう
and please give thoughtful attention
to ways that you can imitate their faith.
子供の頃 「完璧な裁きを
下す神様がいるのなら
Growing up, I wondered,
‘Why does the Supreme Judge, God,
なんで不公正なことや苦しいことが
あるんだろう」と思っていました
allow injustice and suffering?’
自分でも何とかしたいと考えていました
And inside of me,
I had this need to restore justice.
心の中でその気持ちが
めらめらと燃えていました
It was such a burning desire within me.
その思いを胸にロシアに移り
And with that in mind,
姉と暮らし始めました
I moved to Russia to stay with my sister.
姉は聖書を学び始め
She started to study the Bible
学んだことを興奮気味に話していました
and was overflowing with the truth.
2人で夜遅くまで何時間も話しました
We talked for hours till late into the night.
こうしてエホバを知り
エホバとの友情が芽生えました
So that’s when my special relationship
with Jehovah began.
That’s when I got a taste of what it’s like
家族思いのお父さんを持つって
こんな感じなんだ と実感しました
to have a caring Father.
It had been a while
since I was able to feel that.
久々に味わう感覚でした
My baptism date was very exciting.
バプテスマの日は最高でした
兄弟姉妹みんなが私の
大きな家族になりました
The spiritual family I inherited
was very vast.
You can instantly feel the love.
本当に愛をいっぱい感じます
I got baptized,
and it seemed like miracles happened
バプテスマを受けました その後
思いも寄らないうれしいことが
続きました
one after the other.
最高の毎日でした
We had a great life.
そんな時 迫害が始まり
And then
the persecution started
with Brother Christensen,
クリステンセン兄弟に続いて
and then there was a ripple effect
of arrests, one after the other.
兄弟姉妹が相次いで逮捕されました
私も逮捕されました
Then it was our turn.
In June of 2018,
2018年6月
a huge group of armed men came to us,
to our home.
武装した集団がうちに
押し掛けてきました
They represented the ideals of my childhood.
警察官は子供の頃の私の憧れでした
But now these people,
それが今は皮肉なことに
this judicial system,
法を守る立場にある人たちから
became the source of injustice to me.
不当な扱いを受けているんです
I was sitting in a cage,
the same way my bugs used to be in a jar.
おりの中で思いました
瓶に入れたあの虫たちと同じだなって
I guess I felt like they did.
虫もそんなこと 思っていたのかな
In your head
at that moment when you hear the verdict
裁判で 刑務所に入れられるという
判決が言い渡された時
that you’ll stay in prison,
まるで顔面を殴られて
it’s like you’ve been knocked unconscious.
You’ve been hit in the head with something,
意識が遠のくような感覚で
and there’s just a ringing sound
in your ears.
頭の中が真っ白になりました
And so I was taken away in handcuffs.
手錠をされて連れていかれました
Of course, I wasn’t in the best mood.
もちろん いい気分じゃないですよね
But then
でも エレベーターのドアが開いて
the doors of the elevator opened up,
and in front of us,
目に飛び込んできたのは
大勢の兄弟姉妹が
a lot of brothers and sisters
力いっぱいの拍手を
してくれていたんです
were clapping their hands
as hard as they could.
泣いている人もいました
And some were crying,
私をかわいそうに
思ったのではありません
but not crying
because they felt sorry for me.
They cried because they loved us
私たちのことを愛し 誇らしく
思っていたので泣いていたんです
and because they were proud of us.
こういうことはよくあります
That’s what always happens.
When you’re just about to lose
all your strength,
もう駄目だと思った時 エホバは
私たちを元気づけるために
Jehovah does that something for you
that gives you a second wind.
必ず何かをしてくれるんです
あの時もです 拍手 愛 涙
And so, the applause, the love,
the tears,
the shouts,
“Hang in there; everything will be OK!”
掛け声 「頑張って！大丈夫だよ！」
と言ってくれて
—they gave me a second wind.
ほんとに元気が出ました
また走りだす力を取り戻せました
And with renewed strength,
I could run the next part of the race.
One of the guards was so surprised
that he said,
看守の1人が驚いて
「こんなに応援してくれる仲間が
いるんだね」って言っていました
“Now that’s some support you’ve got!”
Yeah.
うん
友達がいないと すごくさみしくて
Without friends, I would be very lonely.
I would constantly be focusing on my illness.
いつも病気のことばかり
考えてしまいます
The day I met Marissa was at a convention.
ある大会でマリッサと友達になりました
She’s a really great friend,
a spiritual friend.
エホバを愛する素晴らしい友達です
When she’d take me
to my hospital appointments,
よく病院に付き添ってくれて
外食もしました
we would eat out.
食事を一緒にすると
すぐに仲良くなれますよね
I think food is just the common language
between everyone, you know.
食べ物の話してると 「これ
おいしい！」とか盛り上がるんですよ
When you talk about food, you know,
it’s like:
“Ah! Yes, we have something to talk about,”
you know.
マリッサと病院に行くのが
いつも楽しみでした
I would be excited when she would take me
to my hospital appointment.
She always makes me laugh, you know.
マリッサは 私が具合が
悪いときも笑わせてくれて
She always helps me have a good time
no matter what.
一緒にいると元気が出ます
Again, friends really help encourage me.
ほんとに 友達の助けって
大きいですよね
Proverbs 17:17 says:
格言 17:17には
「真の友はどんな時にも愛を示す
“A true friend shows love at all times
苦難の時に頼れる
兄弟である」とあります
and is a brother who is born
for times of distress.”
私の場合もそうでした
And I have seen this come true in my life.
銀行の仕事がなくなった時
When I lost my job at the bank,
well, I felt very depressed, troubled, tense.
本当に落ち込み 不安で
気が張り詰めていました
And I have a good friend who I can talk to,
何でも話せる友達がいて
気持ちを打ち明けたらこう言われました
and when I told him how I was feeling,
he told me:
「ねえミゲル 同じ職種に
こだわらない方がいいんじゃないかな？
“Look, Miguel, don’t look for the same
“line of work.
もしかしたら 生活スタイルを
変えた方がいいのかもね
“Maybe what you need to do
is make a change in your life.
オフィスでの仕事だけじゃなくて
“Why don’t you find some simple work
outside of an office for a time?
外でできるような仕事も探してみたら？
“That can help you to keep your eye simple
エホバへの奉仕に
目の焦点が合っていれば
and allow you to provide for your family.”
家族を養えるようになると思うよ」
妻が家族のためにパンを
作るのを見ていました
I watched my wife make bread for our family,
それで ある日言いました
and one day I told her:
「パンを作ってみようかな？
家族のためじゃないよ
“I’m going to make that bread,
but not for our family.
それを売ろうと思うんだ」
I’m going to make it to sell.”
So she told me, “No, are you crazy?”
妻には 「えっ 本気なの？」
と言われました
It was a big change—right?—
銀行で役職に就き 多額の
お金を扱っていた人が
from having a position at a bank
路上でパンを売ることになるなんて
and handling a lot of money
大きな変化ですよね
to selling on the street.
So I told her,
“Look, I’m going to put this hat on,”
「この帽子かぶってみようかな」
と言って
コックさんみたいな帽子をかぶりました
and I put like a chef’s hat on.
そして 「1時間で帰ってくる
売れても売れなくても」と言いました
And I told her,
“I’ll be back in less than an hour,
whether I sell or not.”
約束通り1時間で帰りました
And that’s what happened.
パンが全部売れたのを見て
妻は驚きました
And to her surprise,
I came back without any bread.
So when I got ready
to leave the second time to sell,
2回目に売りに行こうとした時 妻に
she said: “OK. Go, but leave the hat here.”
「行ってらっしゃい でも帽子は
取ってね」って言われちゃいました
アイロンをかける
出張サービスも始めました
I also started to iron clothes
for people in their homes,
この辺りではたいてい女性がする
仕事なので 珍しがられました
and it looked strange
because normally where we live
that type of work is done by a woman.
男性がほかの家に行って
アイロンがけをするなんて
But for a man to go and iron clothes
at someone’s home,
あまり聞かないですよね
you don’t see that.
家でただ腕組みして何もしないでいる
というのは嫌でした
But I didn’t want to just sit back
with my arms crossed
and see what would happen.
No!
とにかく手を動かして家族のために
働かなきゃいけない と思いました
I had to put my hands to work
to earn a living for my family.
1日奉仕に出たら
次の日はアイロンがけ
So I would preach one day,
and the next day I would iron clothes.
また次の日は奉仕に出て その次の日は
パンを売る という感じです
The next day I would preach, and the day
after that I would go out and sell bread.
So my mind was always occupied
on doing something,
いつも忙しくして 王国や家族のことを
考えていたのが良かったと思います
either for the Kingdom or my family.
And that helped me a lot.
とても悲しくて
I was feeling so sad.
どうしてそんな気持ちに
なるのか分からなかったので
I really needed Jehovah’s help
to figure out what was going on with me.
エホバの助けがどうしても必要でした
And I remember
2009年に うつ病についての
記事が出ました
that the 2009 article about depression
came out.
それで分かりました 「ああエホバ
私はうつ病だってことですね」
And I realized: ‘OK, Jehovah,
you’re telling me this is what I have.
‘So now that I realize I have this,
はっきりうつ病だと分かって
できることをしてみようと思いました
I’ve got to figure out how I can manage it.’
それで食習慣を変えました
So I changed my eating habits.
もっと運動もするようにしました
I started exercising a lot more.
I realized that exercising and eating healthy
運動と健康的な食事は
本当に役立ちました
really, really did help.
Also, I made a journal,
また 自分に出ている
うつ病のいろいろな症状を
and I made different sections
セクションごとに分けて
書いていきました
of the different aspects of my depression
that I dealt with.
それぞれのセクションに
In each section, I would put scriptures;
聖句を書いたり
記事を載せたりしました
I would put articles.
また そうした記事に載せられている
挿絵やイラストは
And the illustrations, the pictures,
they speak a lot without saying anything.
強く印象に残ります
エホバは祈りを聞いてくださいますし
Jehovah hears us.
気に掛けてくださっています
Jehovah cares.
刑務所に入れられてしばらくして
After some time in prison,
they transferred me to a different cell.
別の監房に移されました
In it were inmates who followed the orders
同じ監房にいた人たちは
捜査官の言いなりになっていました
of the investigators.
捜査官は囚人たちに指示し
They did everything they could
to other inmates
そこに入ってくる人を
痛めつけるよう言っていました
to make life unbearable.
目的はその人を精神的に
追い詰めることでした
Why did they do this?
To break a person
捜査官に協力して全てを自白すれば
so that they would start to collaborate
with the investigators,
confess to everything, and then be able
to get transferred to another area.
ほかの場所に移してやる
ということだったんです
詩編 37:3には
Psalm 37:3:
“Trust in Jehovah and do what is good.”
「エホバに頼り 善を行え」とあります
I said: “Jehovah, please help me
to stay loyal to you.
「エホバ どうか
あなたに忠実でいられるように
助けてください」と言いました
Please help me.”
My prayers were really simple
私の祈りはとてもシンプルなものでした
—actually like two words: “Jehovah, help!
「エホバ助けて！エホバ助けて！
エホバ助けて！」
Jehovah, help! Jehovah, help!”
Despite how they treated me,
自分がどんな仕打ちを受けても
when I dealt with others,
I tried to treat them with kindness.
相手には親切にする
ということを心掛けました
These people,
受けた仕打ちは
they made life
不快で耐え難いものでしたが
uncomfortable, unbearable,
こちらが親切にしていたら
but when they were treated kindly,
徐々に態度が和らぎました
they started to soften.
私に対する接し方が変わりました
They began to treat me differently.
When I was being transferred
別の監房に移される時
out of that cell,
その監房を取り仕切っていた
囚人が私を呼んで
the inmate who ran the area
called me over to him and said,
「こっちに来て 隣に座れ」
と言いました
“Come sit beside me.”
そこに座ると こう言われました
And I sat down.
Then he said, “If anybody in this prison
touches you,
「おまえに突っ掛かってくる
やつがいたら
ただじゃおかないって言っておけ」
tell him that I’ll come looking for him.”
Then he said, “Get his things”
それから 「荷物を持ってやれ」と
(he told the other prisoners).
ほかの囚人たちに言いました
The cell doors opened
監房の扉が開いて
看守たちは 同じ監房の囚人たちが
and the guards saw
a crowd of inmates
私の荷物を廊下に
運び出すのを見たんですよ
grabbing my things
and putting them out into the hallway.
私は何も持たずに
監房から出てきたんですよ
I left the cell
without having to carry a thing!
看守は静かに扉を閉じました
The guard quietly closed the door.
囚人たちは監房に戻る前
And before the inmates
returned to their cells,
さよならを言い ハグし
they even said goodbye, hugged me,
and said: “Hang in there!
「頑張れ おまえは大丈夫だ」
と言ってくれました
You’re going to be OK.”
看守は扉を閉じて 「ここにどれくらい
いたんだ」と聞いてきました
They went into the cell, and the guard
closed the door and asked me,
“Boy, how long have you been in there?”
「3週間です」と答えました
I said, “Three weeks.”
看守は言いました 「普通は
みんな ぼこぼこにされて
He said: “Well, normally
people leave this cell beaten up,
投げ出されるような感じで出てくるんだ
“and they’re thrown out by the other inmates.
荷物だって運んでもらう人は
見たことがない
“They have to carry their own things,
and that’s if the other inmates
たいていは扉が開いたら
放り投げられるのに」
haven’t thrown their stuff out the door.”
信じられないっていう感じでした
He couldn’t believe what had just happened.
That’s Jehovah.
エホバのおかげです
Exercising, changing my diet,
運動し 食事に気を付け
the publications, journaling
—that was my lifeline.
出版物を読み ノートに
まとめたりすることが
That really actually helped me
for a long time.
長いこと本当に役立ってきました
でも ある時からそれだけでは
対処できなくなりました
But it came to a point
where it stopped working as effectively.
ある時 集会の準備を始めて
さあ行こうと思いました
I remember getting ready,
dressing for the meeting,
and I was fine.
着替えて ドアに向かって歩いて
いったんですが 行けませんでした
I was getting dressed for the meeting
and about to walk out the door,
but I couldn’t.
There was this overwhelming fear
that came over me
突然 どうしようもなく怖くなり
and an overwhelming sadness
that came over me.
悲しい気持ちに襲われました
そして 途方に暮れて
And I just lost it; I just started crying.
ただただ涙が止まりませんでした
I couldn’t get myself together.
どうにもなりませんでした
最悪でした もうほんとに
鬱がひどくて
It was bad.
It got really bad;
my depression got really bad.
私にとって長老たちに助けを
求めに行くというのは
So it was very difficult for me
to approach the brothers
to ask them for help.
とても難しいことでした
But at that time, I knew that if I didn’t,
でもその時 もしそうしないなら
もっと大変なことになる
that
something bad would happen.
そう思いました
それで決めました
「よし 長老たちに牧羊してもらおう」
So I decided: ‘You know what?
I’m going to ask for a shepherding call
with my brothers,’
because I’d never talked about my depression
with the elders at all.
今まで鬱のこと
言ったことなかったんです
初めて長老たちに話しました
This was my first time speaking with them.
長老兄弟の1人は 同じように
鬱と闘っていました
And there was one brother, one of the elders,
who also battled depression.
そして 「専門医に診てもらったことは
ありますか」と聞かれました
And he suggested,
“Have you thought
about seeking medical help?”
病院にかかることは
したくないと思っていました
Seeking professional help
was something I never wanted to do.
I thought that I didn’t need to do it,
その必要はないと思っていましたが
時々自分ではどうにもできなくて
but sometimes there comes a point where
you need additional help
専門的な助けが
やっぱり必要なのかなって
思うことがありました
and what you’re doing is not enough.
In this world, they make you feel
that it’s a bad thing,
一般的に うつ病は何か
悪いこと 恥ずかしいことで
that depression is a dirty word,
そういう病院にかかるなんて
という目で見られます
or that seeking medical help
is something that you don’t do.
でも エホバにもっと十分に
お仕えするためには
But I realized also
that seeking medical help
専門医に診てもらうことも
必要なんだと気付きました
was part of my being able
to worship Jehovah effectively.
できることはしないと
That’s me doing my part.
Not everyone needs to take that step,
but for me, this is what I need to do.
みんながそうすべきっていうことでは
ありませんが 私には必要でした
And I’m glad I did it because of the fact
そうして良かったと思います
これまでこんなに気分が晴れたことは
that I’ve never ever felt this good
全然ありませんでした
in my life.
良かったです
About a year later,
約1年後
we were released.
釈放されました
But my wife and I understood
妻も私も
that they could put me back in prison again,
私がまた刑務所に入ることに
なるだろうと思っていたので
so
we needed to use
the time until then to the full
できる限り時間を有効に
使わなければ と考えました
in the best way possible.
思い浮かんだのは
So, what did we do?
詩編 119:165です
Psalm 119:165:
「豊かな平和はあなたの律法を
愛する人たちのもの」
“Abundant peace belongs to those
who love your law.”
家族の崇拝をして
We had family worship,
聖書を読んで 一緒に祈りました
read the Bible, and prayed together.
That’s how I spent my four months of freedom.
自由な4カ月間を
そのように過ごしました
そして また刑務所に入りました
Then I was put into prison
3年間です
for three years.
When they told me
about my cancer being gone,
がんが消えたと聞いた時は
もうほんとに跳び上がるほど
うれしかったです
I was really happy; I was ecstatic.
I was like: ‘Finally I’m going
to get to do normal things
私くらいの年の子ができることが
やっと普通にできるようになる
と思いました
‘that a kid my age should be able to do.
I don’t need to be afraid
or anxious anymore.’
もう怖く思ったり
心配することはないんです
残念なことに がんが再発しました
Unfortunately, I did relapse again,
and basically right now
my present condition is
今のところできる治療は
これ以上もうない と言われました
there’s nothing really more to do.
They’re just waiting
to let nature take its course basically,
今はもうこのまま この生活を
続けるしかありません
and that’s it.
それだけです
In harmony with Ephesians 4:26,
まず 現実を受け止めなければ
いけませんし
悲しみや怒りは湧き上がってきます
I had to let myself process the news
でもエフェソス 4:26を
思い出しました
and let myself be sad and be angry.
もちろん そういう感情を
Let yourself feel those feelings;
押し殺さなくてもいいとは
思っていますが
do not try to repress them.
But you can control
your thoughts and your actions.
自分の感情や行動は
コントロールできます
Pretty much my whole life
has revolved around my illness,
病気になって生活が
大きく変わりましたが
何に目を向けたらいいかを学べました
but I’ve learned how to shift focus.
自分のことばかり考えないことです
自分とは違うけど
I just don’t focus on myself all the time.
I focus on others and their trials,
同じように大変な試練に遭っている
兄弟姉妹のことを考えました
which are different but just as hard.
jw.orgのニュースルームの
記事を読みました
You read the stories
on jw.org in the Newsroom.
ロシアの兄弟姉妹についての記事です
The Russian brothers and sisters,
兄弟たちはとても大変な状況にいます
I pray for them constantly because
それで 兄弟姉妹のことを
いつも祈っています
they are going through a very tough time.
確かに 「受けるより
与える方が幸福」です
“There is [definitely] more happiness
in giving than receiving.”
私たちの場合も この言葉の通りでした
And in our situation, this proved true.
与えるならつらい気持ちが
和らぐというのは
I would say
this really helps to relieve your pain.
本当だと思います
自分に注意が向いていると
If you focus on yourself,
your pain gets worse.
ますますつらくなります
ほかの人のことや その人の
問題について考えるなら
When you focus on others
and on their problems,
your pain lessens, diminishes.
自分の痛みは小さくなります
プリビエット
Hello!
こんにちは
アントワネット
Antoinette, I was so—
ああ こうやって話す機会が
もらえるって聞いて
When I was told
that we would talk with each other,
すっごく楽しみにしていましたよ
this was something very special for me.
Same for me too.
私もです 兄弟と会えるって聞いて
When the brothers told me as well
とっても楽しみにしていました
about meeting you, I was really excited.
Thank you for your prayers
in behalf of the brothers in Russia.
ロシアの兄弟たちのために
祈ってくれて本当にありがとう
力になります
They are precious.
アントワネットのことを聞いて
励まされました
We can learn so much from you.
ありがとうございます
Thank you.
そう言っていただけて
とてもうれしいです
It’s really nice of you to say that.
兄弟も私も とても大変なことを
たくさん経験してきましたよね
We’ve both been through very many hardships.
I’m sure prison was super hard.
刑務所 すごい大変だと思います
You know, in prison,
us brothers had a saying,
刑務所の中で兄弟たちは
こんなことを言っていました
「もし 『これから状況は
“If you ask: ‘How much worse can it get?’
どれほどひどくなるんだろう』
と思っているんだったら
you won’t have to wait long to find out.”
答えはすぐに分かるよ」
つまり 「状況はどれほどひどく
なるんだろう」と思っていると
Or in other words, when you think,
‘How much worse can it get?’
状況はどんどん悪くなっているように
感じるということです
for sure something worse is bound to happen.
And when we received our sentence,
we thought:
判決が言い渡された時
「ああ 最悪だ」と思いました
‘Well, that’s it.
That’s the worst that could happen.’
その後も 思っていた通り
And then, of course, it got worse.
状況は悪くなりました
Upon arrival at the prison,
刑務所に着いた時
激しく殴打され
we were beaten up
何時間も屈辱的な扱いを受けました
and for hours we were humiliated.
「どれほどひどくなるんだろう」
と思いました
We thought, ‘How much worse can it get?’
Then the next day, we were told,
次の日 「おまえは懲罰用の監房に
入るんだ」と言われました
“You are going to the punishment cell.”
We thought,
‘Well, how much worse can it get?’
また 「どれだけひどくなるんだ？」
と思いました
コロナの患者が 最初は
ワンフロアだけだったのが
At first, it started with one floor,
then it went to another floor,
and then the whole entire hospital.
ほかのフロアにも来て 全てのフロアが
Every floor had COVID patients.
コロナの患者でいっぱいになりました
That was some of the hardest nursing
that I’ve ever done in my life
これまで何年も看護師の
仕事をしてきた中で
こんなに大変だったことはありません
in all of my years of nursing.
And we lost a lot of good nurses
一緒にコロナ患者のために
一生懸命働いてきた
who were right in the trenches with me
who were in there doing their best.
優秀な看護師たちが
たくさん亡くなりました
患者を助けようと頑張っていたのに⋯
We lost a lot of good people.
Even though I was on medication to help me,
鬱の薬を飲みながら
仕事をしていましたが
it still didn’t take the depression away.
鬱の症状はなくなりませんでした
You’re like: ‘What’s the point?
「これに意味があるのかしら？
‘I can’t save anyone.
頑張っても誰も助けられない」
と思いました
I can’t, I can’t help anyone.’
がっかりして 本当に
心が折れてしまいました
It was devastating.
It truly, truly was devastating.
Have you ever felt as Feliks did
when he asked,
皆さんもフェリクスのように
「これから状況はどれほど
ひどくなるんだろう」と
“How much worse can it get?”
思ったことがありますか
Nevertheless, a spiritual person
でも エホバに目を向ける人は
大変なことが起きるたびに
can see each new challenge
それをエホバに頼る機会と考えます
as an opportunity to rely on Jehovah.
これからこの動画の
結びの部分を見ながら
As we watch
the concluding part of this video,
please take note of how Jehovah strengthened
エホバが兄弟姉妹を
どのように力づけてきたか
these brothers and sisters
友としてどのように支えてきたかに
注目しましょう
and deepened their friendship with him.
Think about your own circumstances
ご自分の今の状況と 試練に遭った時
and the ways that Jehovah
has helped you through trials,
エホバがどのように助けて
くださったかを考えましょう
エホバはこれからも皆さんを
助けてくださいます
and have full confidence
that he will continue to do so.
そのことを確信してください
その後 「どれほどひどく
なるんだろう」と
And then I decided
that I was going to stop asking,
考えることはやめたんです
“How much worse could it get?”
エホバに 忍耐する力と喜びを
持てますように と祈りました
I asked Jehovah for endurance
and joy for that day—just for that day.
その日1日 1日ごとにです
And at those times, I just
エホバに泣きながら
自分の気持ちを
cry to Jehovah,
お話ししました
talk to Jehovah about how I’m feeling,
この状況に
平和な気持ちで耐えられるよう
and just ask for his peace
to help me to deal.
祈りました
I’ve talked to Jehovah
very intimately and personally
ほんとに心細くて
ここまでエホバに自分の心を
注ぎ出して祈ったことは
but never like I have
when I was so alone there.
今までありませんでした
I realized that I was going to die.
もう自分は死ぬんじゃないか
と思いました
I asked Jehovah if he saw enough good in me,
「もし私に良いところがあると
見てくださっているのでしたら
that he would just resurrect me
新しい世界で復活して
and that I’d love to be in his new world
主人や子供たちに会えるように
してください」と祈りました
and see my husband again and my children.
そして ここまで生きてこれたことに
感謝しました
And I thanked him so much
for the life that I had.
そうすると
And I felt such a peace
今まで感じたことがないような
平和な気持ちに包まれました
like I’d never felt before.
そのうち
And then
エホバが抜け出せるように
してくださったのを感じました
I just knew it was Jehovah getting me out.
エホバの指示は簡単なことで
The obedience, just doing what we were told,
ただ従いなさい
ということだったんです
it came from Jehovah, and it was so simple.
エホバは命を守って
祝福してくださいました
That gave him something to bless,
and it may have saved my life.
あまり迷惑を掛けたく
なかったんですけど
I just never wanted to be a burden on people,
but
国内の各地から兄弟姉妹たちが来て
the brothers and sisters
had come from all over the country
to do work for this house
and the other houses—all of them.
うちも周りの家も
全部修理してくれました
気に掛けてくれてる
They made me feel wanted,
愛されてる と感じます
and they made me feel loved.
エホバはこんな私のことにも
目を留めてくださっているんです
To feel like Jehovah cared enough
to give attention to me,
ああ 本当にありがたいことです
I
just felt so unworthy.
それに みんなが
And here all these people
are here taking care of me.
皆さんが面倒を見てくれています
And you just look at them,
and then you think:
この組織にいられて幸せです
「私もみんなのように
もっと愛を示したい」と
‘I’m part of this organization.
I’ve got to do better.
I’ve got to be like them
and make other people happy.’
兄弟姉妹を見て思いました
同じようにうつ病と闘っている人を
助けられると
When I’m able to help people
who are battling depression,
I feel like Jehovah is using me in that way,
そういう仕方でエホバが私を
用いてくださっていると感じて
and it makes me happy
that I can be of use to Jehovah.
とてもうれしいです
It’s good to feel—
It’s so nice to feel good again,
また気分が爽やかになって
幸せに感じて 笑って過ごせて
to feel happy again, to be able to smile,
何気ないものを見ても
すてきだって思えるし
to be able to take in enjoyment
of the small things, you know,
in Jehovah’s creation
そうですね エホバの創造物とか
—and, you know, just be happy that I’m alive.
生きていることが ただ本当に幸せです
So
yeah, yeah.
うん そうですね
今は仕事が見つかって
Now I have a stable job.
ホームセンターで働いています
I work at a hardware store.
心は平和です
試練によって強くなれましたし
And I feel at peace.
The adversities have made me stronger,
and overall, I have
a much closer relationship with Jehovah.
結果的にエホバと
もっと親しくなれました
パンは今も作ってますよ
But I’m still making bread.
家でのアイロンがけは私の仕事です
And at home, yeah,
I’m the one who irons the clothes.
しばらくして 国外退去に
なることが分かりました
After a while, I found out
that I was being deported.
列車を降りた時のことを覚えています
I remember getting off the train.
私は裏口から出てきましたが
They took me through the back door,
妻のジェーニャは正面口で
待っていました
but my wife, Zhenya,
was standing at the main entrance.
She was on the phone. She couldn’t see me.
妻は電話しながら正面口を見ていて
She was looking at the main entrance.
私に気付きませんでした
私はかばんを投げ出して
And I threw my bag down as I ran to her.
妻の方に走っていきました
She could see from the corner of her eyes
someone was running.
妻は 誰かが走ってくるのが横に見えて
ちょっと驚いて 怖がっていました
She was a little confused, even scared.
そこでついに
And there I was
最愛の人を抱き締めることができました
hugging the person I loved the most.
It was one
of the most beautiful days of my life.
この日のことは決して忘れません
Hi.
こんにちは
Privet.
プリビエット
Hello.
こんにちは
アントワネットが 私たちのことや
When I heard that you were praying for us
ロシアの兄弟姉妹のことを
祈ってくれていると聞いて
and for the brothers and sisters in Russia,
私もフェリクスもほんと励まされました
it really encouraged me and Feliks.
私たちも見倣いたいと思います
It’s such an example for me personally.
フェリクスが昨日祈りの中で
We mentioned it in our prayer yesterday;
アントワネットが兄弟姉妹のことを
心から気に掛けていて
Feliks was saying
that you are a great example
of how we need
素晴らしいお手本だ と言っていて
to genuinely care
for our brothers and sisters.
私もそう思いました
アントワネットのこと
愛して気に掛けているよ
We love you very much.
さよなら
Goodbye.
お会いできてうれしかったです
It was nice meeting you.
Goodbye.
さよなら
私のがんは今は治りませんが
My cancer is uncurable,
but I know the cure is in the new system.
新しい体制で治ると分かっています
So that’s the cure!
そこで完全に治ります
「その時になったら私は何を
やっているかな」ってよく考えます
I like to imagine, ‘When that time happens,
what will I be doing?’
がんがすっかり治って 喜んで
跳びはねていると思います
Obviously, I’m going to be jumping for joy
because I’m going to be rid of my cancer.
食べたことのない
おいしい食べ物を食べたり
I’m going to enjoy food
that we never really got to enjoy,
いろんな動物と遊んだりしたいです
and I’m going to have so many animals.
I’m going to make a house.
I’m going to learn how to make a house.
家も造りたいです
家の造り方も教えてもらわないと
Peace in this world is not the absence
この世界で平和な心を
持っているからといって 病気
of illness,
危ないこと
danger,
persecution,
迫害
失業を経験しないという
ことではありません
or economic problems.
この世界で平和な心を
持っているというのは
Peace in this world
is listening to Jehovah’s guidance,
エホバの言うことを聞き
praying to Jehovah constantly,
エホバにいつも祈り
エホバの言葉と約束を
meditating on Jehovah’s Word
and his promises.
思い巡らすことです
そして いつも支えてくれる
良い友達を持つことや
Peace in this world is also
having good friends by our side
ユーモアのセンスをなくさないことです
and having a good sense of humor.
平和は周囲の状況
What I’ve learned from all of this
起きていること
is peace isn’t from what’s outside,
経験していることから来るのではない
ということが分かりました
from what’s going on,
or from what you’re experiencing.
平和とは内面の状態のことで それは
I’ve learned that peace is on the inside,
and that comes from Jehovah.
エホバから来るんです
今紹介した兄弟姉妹は
These examples we’ve just seen
「私たちと同じようにいろいろな
感情を持つ」普通の人たちです
are of ordinary people
“with feelings like ours.”
それでも 厳しい試練に遭った時に
Yet, they felt peace
even when confronting serious trials.
平和な心を持ち続けました
どのようにそうしたのでしょうか
How did they do it?
ミゲルは失業した時
When Miguel lost his job,
エホバへの奉仕に目を向け続け
he kept his focus on serving Jehovah
家族を養うため職種に
こだわり過ぎないで
and he was not too proud to do humble work
どんな仕事も進んで行いました
to provide for his family.
マーガレットは 自然災害の
備えをしていました
Margaret was prepared for a natural disaster,
そして 大変な状況の時にも
ずっとエホバに祈りました
and throughout her ordeal,
she prayed to Jehovah.
うつ病と闘っていたニッキーは
While struggling with depression,
Nikki did research using our publications
役立つ情報を出版物から探すとともに
and asked for help from the elders.
長老たちに助けを求めました
フェリクスは残忍な迫害に遭いましたが
Even when facing brutal persecution,
そういう仕打ちをする人にも
親切に接しました
Feliks showed kindness to his persecutors.
そのようにするなら
He knew that the way he responded
本当のクリスチャンであることを示せる
ということを知っていたのです
would reflect Christian qualities.
アントワネットも素晴らしいですね
And dear Antoinette,
がんが治る見込みはないと
分かっていても
despite her diagnosis,
focuses not on herself
自分の問題ではなく
兄弟姉妹のことに目を向けていました
but on helping others.
アントワネットも 私たち全ても
As she said, the cure for her
病気が治るのは神の王国が治める時です
—as it is for all of us—
is God’s Kingdom.
If you are experiencing trials,
今試練に遭っていますか
自分にできることに目を向け
他の人を助け 感謝し
focus on what you can control,
help others,
be grateful,
エホバとエホバの組織に
心から頼ってください
and rely on Jehovah and his organization.
If you are not experiencing serious trials,
厳しい試練に遭っていない方は
do what you can to prepare for them
今後の試練に備えて
エホバへの信仰を強めてください
by building yourself up spiritually.
心配しないようにしましょう
Do not be anxious.
Fear of what might happen
心配しているようなことは
is often worse than the trial itself.
実際には起きないかもしれません
エホバを信頼しましょう
Trust in Jehovah, and be assured
エホバが友を見捨てる
ということは決してありません
that he will never abandon his friends.
The dear brothers and sisters
whom we’ve just listened to
ここでご紹介した兄弟姉妹たちは
エホバとの強い絆を保っています
are doing well spiritually.
We thank them
for participating in these interviews.
インタビューに応じてくださり
ありがとうございます
We’d also like to thank
all our brothers and sisters
パンデミック中に いつも以上に
ハードな環境で働いた
working in the medical field
医療従事者の兄弟姉妹にも
感謝をお伝えします
who have gone the extra mile
during this pandemic.
ヤコブ 5:11にはこうあります
James 5:11 reads:
“We consider happy those who have endured.
「私たちは 忍耐した人は
幸せであると考えます
“You have heard of the endurance of Job
皆さんはヨブの忍耐について聞き
ヨブがエホバのおかげでどんな結末を
迎えたかを知っています
“and have seen the outcome Jehovah gave,
that Jehovah is very tender in affection
and merciful.”
エホバは優しい愛情にあふれ
憐れみ深い方なのです」
The blessings we receive by enduring trials
今試練に耐えることによって
得られるものは
can strengthen us for the future
今後難しい状況を経験する時に
役立ちます
and help us to become the kind of person
エホバに喜ばれる人になる上でも
役立ちます
that Jehovah wants us to be.
The inner peace and joy we experience
難しい状況でも経験できる
心の平和や喜びは
is a gift from Jehovah.
エホバからの贈り物です
As these brothers and sisters
from around the world
こうした世界中の兄弟姉妹の
経験からも分かるように
have reminded us,
エホバは素晴らしいお父さんです
we need never doubt
that our wonderful heavenly Father will bless
何があってもエホバを
愛し続ける人全てを
必ず祝福してくださるのです
all those who continue loving him.
インタビューに答えてくださった
We thank all of the sisters and brothers
who were interviewed
全ての兄弟姉妹に感謝いたします
for their sincere comments
and for allowing us to benefit and learn
from their experiences.
話してくださった経験から
多くのことを学びました
兄弟姉妹の言葉から
Those candid interviews show
that we can remain at peace
厳しい試練に耐えなければならない時も
even when enduring severe trials.
平和を保てるということが分かりました
Jehovah always supports and cares for us,
his loyal servants.
エホバはご自分に仕える人を
必ず支え 世話してくださいます
The time has now come
for the baptism discourse.
さて バプテスマの話の
時間となりました
We encourage all baptism candidates
to pay particular attention.
バプテスマ希望者の皆さんは
注意を払ってお聞きください
How does walking in Jehovah’s way
bring peace?
エホバの道はどのように
平和をもたらしますか
How can we stay on the road
to everlasting life?
どうすれば命への道にとどまれますか
Please listen carefully
as Brother William Turner,
奉仕委員会の援助者
ウィリアム・ターナー兄弟が
a helper to the Service Committee,
次の主題で話してくださいます
delivers the talk
“Go On Walking ‘in the Way of Peace.’”
「『平和の道』を進み続けてください」
世界中のバプテスマ希望者の皆さん
We cannot express
to you baptism candidates around the world
私たちは この時を共に迎えられる
ことを本当にうれしく思います
how much of a privilege it is for us
to share in this occasion with you.
You are following through
on the most important decision
皆さんは人生で一番重要な決定をし
you’ve ever made
神に献身したことを
—to make it known publicly
はっきり表そうとしておられます
that you have dedicated your life to God.
We know your situations vary.
状況はさまざまでしょう
Some of you candidates
were raised knowing about Jehovah,
エホバについて教えられて成長し
but you had to develop your own
personal relationship with him.
エホバとの関係を築いてきた方も
おられます
Others of you may be taking this step
もっと最近になってエホバについて
学び始めた方もおられます
after learning about Jehovah more recently.
But whatever your circumstances,
これまでの歩みは
likely it was a journey
いずれにしても旅のようです
—a figurative road
you had to travel to get to this point.
今の地点まで努力して
進んでこられました
In fact, the Bible also compares true worship
実際 聖書にも 真の崇拝を道に
to a road, a path,
旅をして歩んでいく道に
例えている所があります
or a walkway that has to be traveled.
At Acts 9:2,
例えば 1世紀のクリスチャン会衆が
設立されていく中で
as the first-century
Christian congregation was being established,
新しく確立された崇拝の方式を指して
Jesus’ disciples used the term “The Way”
「この道」という表現が
使徒 9:2で使われています
to designate their newly established
form of worship.
They understood that as baptized Christians,
弟子たちは バプテスマを受けた
クリスチャンとして
they were walking on a new path
新しい道を歩んでいること
and every aspect of their lives was involved.
それには生活の全てが関係することを
理解していました
And that’s going to be
the case for you as well.
皆さんの場合も同じです
In fact, note how the Bible describes this.
この点が聖書で何と述べられているか
エフェソス 4章をお開きください
Turn with me, please,
to the book of Ephesians.
And note what is stated
in Ephesians chapter 4,
ご一緒にエフェソスのクリスチャンへの
手紙 4:22-24を
and we’ll read verses 22 through 24.
読みましょう
There it says: “You were taught
to put away the old personality
「皆さんは 古い人格を
脱ぎ捨てるようにと教えられました
“that conforms
to your formal course of conduct
その人格は 以前の生き方に
基づくもので
“and that is being corrupted
according to its deceptive desires.
悪い欲望に引きずられて
腐敗していきます
“And you should continue to be made new
考え方を新しくする努力を続けましょう
“in your dominant mental attitude,
そして 新しい人格を身に着けましょう
“and should put on the new personality
その人格は神の意志に沿って
形作られるものであり
“that was created according to God’s will
本当の正しさと忠実さに
基づいています」
in true righteousness and loyalty.”
So like the first-century Christians,
1世紀のクリスチャンと同じく
皆さんもエホバについての
真理を知りました
you have come to know
the truth about Jehovah.
And the things you’ve learned
そして 学んだことに基づいて
have led you to become baptism candidates.
バプテスマを受けることにしました
Like all of God’s people,
神に仕える人として 皆さんは
22節にあるように
you’ve done what verse 22 states,
“put away the old personality.”
「古い人格を脱ぎ捨て」ました
But there in verse 23,
でも23節にあるように 私たちは
we must also “continue to be made new
「考え方を新しくする努力を続け」る
必要もあります
in [our] dominant mental attitude.”
This involves our thoughts
私たちの考え
—what we allow our mind to dwell on.
何を考え続けるかということです
Now, you know, the footnote for that verse
さらにこの節の脚注には
「精神的傾向」とあります
indicates this term could also be rendered
as “the force actuating [our] mind”
「精神的傾向」には
or literally translated
“to the spirit of your mind.”
欲求や気質や動機が含まれます
In the English language,
実際ここで使われている
元のギリシャ語には 人の心から生じ
perhaps you’ve heard someone say
that they are in good spirits
or you’ve heard someone
described as being mean-spirited.
何らかの言動へと
駆り立てる力という意味があります
それで 私たちは考え方を
変化させるとともに
Well, that’s a description
of one’s dominant mental attitude
—one’s thoughts and motivations.
人を動かす動機の部分も
It’s what moves us to act the way that we do.
新しくしていく必要があると
言えるでしょう
Our goal as baptized servants of Jehovah
バプテスマを受けて
エホバに仕える人として
is to gain a dominant mental attitude
私たちは神の考えに沿った考え方
that aligns and is in harmony
精神的傾向を持つことを目指します
with God’s thoughts.
Now, that won’t always be easy.
簡単ではありません
It takes time and a lot of effort.
時間と努力が必要です
Those who walk
in the way of peace
平和の道を歩む人は試練に遭うものです
often encounter trials.
And to stay on that road,
その道にとどまるには
we must be willing to make sacrifices.
犠牲を払わなければなりません
Like some of those first-century Christians,
1世紀のクリスチャンのように
we may have to endure direct persecution.
迫害を受けることもあるでしょう
But if we continue to walk in Jehovah’s way,
でもエホバの道を歩み続けるなら
we’re going to be happy
幸せになり
and Jehovah is going to bless us.
エホバの祝福を受けます
At Luke 1:79, he assures us
ルカ 1:79で エホバは
that he will “guide our feet
in the way of peace.”
「私たちを平和の道に導く」と
保証しています
That’s a comforting thought, isn’t it?
安心できますね
So we’re excited.
バプテスマ希望者の皆さんが
We’re excited that you baptism candidates
この道を歩み始めていることを
本当にうれしく思います
have undertaken this journey.
And know that you have
850万ものエホバの証人が
some eight and a half million
other Witnesses on this road with you.
皆さんと一緒にこの道を歩んでいます
And today,
今日私たちは
it is our honor and privilege to welcome you
バプテスマ希望者の皆さんを
—to welcome you to Jehovah’s way of peace
エホバの平和の道と
「命に至る⋯⋯道」に
and “the road leading off into life.”
心から歓迎いたします
As we go through our discussion today,
今日のこの話では3つの質問を考えます
we’re going to answer three questions.
First, why is it important
that we do not give up
1つ目は エホバの平和の道を歩むのを
諦めないことはなぜ重要か
on walking in Jehovah’s way of peace?
Second,
2つ目は エホバの道を歩むことは
どのように平和をもたらすか
how does walking
in Jehovah’s way bring us peace?
And third, what can we do
3つ目は エホバの平和の道を
歩み続けるために
to continue walking
in Jehovah’s way of peace?
どんなことができるかです
Well, let’s address our first question:
では1つ目の
エホバの平和の道を歩むのを
Why is it important that we do not give up
諦めないことは
なぜ重要かを考えましょう
on walking in Jehovah’s way of peace?
Now, to answer that, let’s turn, please,
ご一緒にコリント第二 4章を開いて
答えを見つけましょう
to 2 Corinthians chapter 4.
And we’ll note
コリント第二 4:16-18
2 Corinthians 4:16-18.
There it reads:
読みます
“Therefore, we do not give up,
「ですから 私たちは諦めません
“but even if the man
we are outside is wasting away,
たとえ私たちの外面は
衰えていくとしても
“certainly the man we are inside
is being renewed from day to day.
内面は日々新しくされていくのです
“For though the tribulation
is momentary and light,
苦難はつかの間で軽いものですが
“it works out for us a glory
はるかに重みのある永遠の栄光を
“that is of more and more
surpassing greatness and is everlasting;
私たちにもたらします
“while we keep our eyes,
私たちは 見えるものではなく
“not on the things seen,
but on the things unseen.
見えないものに目を留めます
“For the things seen are temporary,
見えるものは一時的ですが
but the things unseen are everlasting.”
見えないものは永遠だからです」
Do you see why we can’t give up?
諦めないのはなぜですか
It’s because being one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
エホバの証人でいるためには
活発に奉仕を続け
requires that we remain active
平和の道にとどまる必要があるからです
and persevere in the way of peace.
You dear candidates have not given up
in your efforts to please Jehovah
バプテスマ希望者の皆さんは
エホバを喜ばせ エホバに仕える資格を
得る努力を諦めませんでした
and to qualify to become part of his people.
And why is that?
なぜですか
It’s because of your love for him.
エホバを愛しているからです
And you know that any trials
and obstacles you face now
神の新しい世界での
永遠の生活に比べれば
are “momentary and light”
今の試練や問題は
when compared to an eternity
in God’s new world.
「つかの間で軽いもの」と
言うことができます
Today, you will enter
into a special relationship
今日 皆さんはエホバ神との
特別な関係に入ります
with Jehovah God.
So don’t let anyone or anything
誰にも何にも
その関係を損なわれないように
してください
jeopardize that relationship.
Let it be something that you cherish
その絆を大切にしましょう
because that relationship is everlasting.
永遠に続くものだからです
エホバの平和の道を歩み続けてください
So keep walking in Jehovah’s way of peace.
Focus on what it means
to have him as a Friend,
エホバを友とし エホバに歩みを導いて
いただくのは本当に素晴らしいことです
to have him guiding your steps.
If you don’t give up,
諦めないなら
then despite any trials you face,
どんな試練に直面するとしても
you will continue
to enjoy Jehovah’s blessings.
エホバの祝福をずっと味わえます
And we’re confident that you can do so.
皆さんならそうできます
But to highlight how this can be done,
では この点を示す経験を今日は
at this time,
インディラ・アルフォンソ姉妹から
お聞きしましょう
we’re pleased to introduce
Sister Indira Alfonso.
Sister Alfonso was baptized in 2006
アルフォンソ姉妹は2006年に
バプテスマを受け
and now serves with her husband
as Bethel family members in Warwick.
今は夫婦で ウォーウィック・ベテルで
奉仕しておられます
Sister Alfonso,
アルフォンソ姉妹 どのようにして
エホバの証人になったか
can you tell us a little about your journey,
how you became associated
with Jehovah’s Witnesses?
ご自分の経験をお話しいただけますか
Yes, I was born in Cuba,
私はキューバで生まれ 9歳の時に
母とアメリカに来ました
but my mom and I moved
to the United States when I was nine.
Even though I was young,
I felt it was important to look for God.
私は 小さい時から神を探していました
So whenever we moved,
I would visit the local churches in the area,
それで引っ越すたびに
いつも地元の教会に行き
バプテスマも何度か受けました
even getting baptized in a number of them.
When I was 11, my mom
let me move in with my aunt,
11歳の時 私だけエホバの証人の
おばの所に住むことになりました
who was one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
おばは私が会衆の開拓者の姉妹と聖書を
学んでもいいか尋ね 母は同意しました
And from there, she asked my mom
if I could study with a pioneer sister
from her congregation, and my mom agreed.
小さい時から神について知りたいと
思っておられたんですね
Well, it’s nice to see
that even at a young age
you had a spiritual need.
So during this time
leading up to your baptism
その後 エホバの証人として
バプテスマを受けるまでの間に
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
did you encounter any trials
that threatened to make you give up?
諦めそうになる試練が何かありましたか
Yes, I did.
I made changes very quickly.
はい ありました 私はすぐに変化して
I stopped celebrating holidays
and stopped praying to idols.
祝日を祝うのをやめ
偶像に祈るのもやめました
But these changes
were very strange to my mom
でも母は奇妙に思ったようで
—just difficult for her to understand.
なぜそうするか
理解してくれませんでした
She was really afraid
that I was being brainwashed.
洗脳されたんではないかと思ったんです
So after studying for several months,
何カ月か聖書レッスンをした後
母のもとに戻ることになり
she had me move back in with her,
聖書レッスンも集会の出席も
できなくなってしまいました
which meant the end of my studies
and no more attending meetings.
It wasn’t long before my association
すぐに私の言動は周りの人の影響を
受けるようになりました
was affecting my speech and my behavior.
I found myself easily influenced
to even celebrate my birthday again.
自分の誕生日も また祝うように
なってしまいました
I could feel I was moving further away
from Jehovah instead of closer to him.
エホバに近づくのではなく
離れていっているのが分かりました
そういうことがあったんですね
I’m sorry to hear that, Sister Alfonso.
So, what helped you not to give up
諦めずに平和の道を歩み続ける上で
何が助けになりましたか
and to go on walking in the way of peace?
What helped me was the scripture
at Matthew 10:37,
マタイ 10:37の
「私より父親や母親に愛情を抱く人は
私の弟子として
where Jesus said:
“Whoever has greater affection for father
ふさわしくありません」という
言葉が助けになりました
or mother than for me is not worthy of me.”
I realized that a peaceful
relationship with Jehovah
エホバとの平和が家族との平和を
意味するとは限りません
might mean no peace with my family.
母を真理に引き寄せるには
But I knew that if I were
to ever gain my mom,
正しい道を歩むのを諦めては
いけないと気付きました
I had to walk with Jehovah
the right way and not give up.
So one night, I prayed to him,
それである夜 許しと助けを求めて
泣きながら祈りました
crying for forgiveness
and asking for his help.
And to my surprise,
a few days later without any explanation,
驚いたことに数日後 母は何の
説明もなく 私をおばの所に戻しました
my mom had me move back in with my aunt.
So I resumed my Bible studies,
聖書レッスンを再開し
and a year later
at the age of 15, I got baptized.
1年後 15歳の時に
バプテスマを受けました
エホバが姉妹の祈りを
聞いてくださったんですね
Jehovah clearly heard
and answered your prayer.
Since then, have you seen
continued evidence of Jehovah’s guidance?
その後もエホバの導きを
経験してこられましたか
A good friend helped me to adjust the way
I was communicating with my mom.
母との関係を改善するよう
友達が助けてくれました
So one day, I called her and expressed to her
how much I truly appreciate and love her.
それである日 母に電話し
どれほど愛し感謝しているかを伝え
気まずいままでいたくないと伝えました
I didn’t want us to be distant anymore.
I explained to her
that my love for her had never changed,
エホバへの愛が一番だけど
お母さんへの愛は決して
変わっていないと説明しました
but my love for Jehovah had come first.
So that conversation
was a turning point for us.
その時の会話がきっかけとなって
Now we have had many positive discussions,
今では良い話し合いができ
私の決定をよく理解してくれています
and she’s much more understanding
of my decision.
Seeing Jehovah’s guidance in my life
エホバが導いてくれているのが分かり
makes me determined
to continue walking in his way of peace.
平和の道を歩み続ける決意が
強まっています
姉妹 どうもありがとうございました
Thank you so much, Sister Alfonso.
良い経験を話してくださり
感謝いたします
We appreciate
your faithful example and comments.
では 2つ目の点を考えます
Well, let’s address our second point.
How does walking in Jehovah’s way
bring us peace?
エホバの道を歩むことは
どのように平和をもたらすでしょうか
And to answer this,
we’re going to compare the path,
これからその答えを考えるに当たり
皆さんが歩んできた命に至る道を
or journey, you’ve taken on the road to life
with a literal road, or walkway.
文字通りの道と比べてみましょう
And in making this comparison,
we find a number of similarities.
その2つの道には
どんな共通点があるでしょうか
First, both roads have boundaries,
2つの道のどちらにも 境界
a purpose, and a destination.
役割 目的地があります
Well, let’s start
with that first one: boundaries.
では 最初は境界について考えましょう
On a literal road, we may see “Yield”
文字通りの道路には
「一時停止」や「進入禁止」の標識
or “Do Not Enter” signs,
ガードレールやセンターラインがあって
guardrails on the side of the road,
or lines on the road
to help us stay in our lane.
通れる所が決まっているのを
ご存じでしょう
Well, those are boundaries.
境界があるわけです
And those boundaries
are there for our protection
それは私たちを
保護するためのものであり
because if we step outside of them,
無視したり 守らなかったりするなら
we risk getting hurt or lost.
事故に遭うかもしれません
危険です
It would be great if we could tell you
バプテスマ希望者の皆さんが
バプテスマの後
that as you continue
on the road to life after your baptism,
命に至る道を歩んでいく時
we would love to say that the rest
of your journey is smooth sailing.
「もう後は何も問題ありません
安全に旅を続けられます」と
言えればよいのですが
You’ll have nothing but safe travels.
But the reality is
現実はそうではありません
難しい問題に直面して信仰が試されます
that you will face challenges
and tests of your faith.
The Devil will make sure of it.
悪魔がそうさせます
He will make sure
that you are confronted
皆さんを誘惑に遭わせようと
狙っています
with temptations.
He wants to do whatever he can
あなたとエホバとの特別な関係を
損なうためなら 何でもするつもりです
to damage
your special relationship with Jehovah.
But we’re confident that you can succeed.
でも 皆さんは負けないと
確信しています
You can be successful and avoid danger
エホバの平和の道の
境界の中にとどまるなら
if you remain within the boundaries
安全に旅を続けることができ
of Jehovah’s way of peace.
危険を避けられます
Now, how do you stay
within those boundaries?
どうすれば境界内にとどまれますか
By continuing to learn
about Jehovah’s laws
これからもエホバの律法と
原則について学び続け
and principles and obeying them.
それに従うことです
That obedience will not only protect you,
従順であるなら 守られるだけでなく
but it will give you inner peace
やましいところのない良心を持ち
—peace that comes
from having a clean conscience.
心の平和も得ることができます
The next similarity between a literal road
次に考える実際の道路と
命に至る道の共通点は
and being on the road to life
that we’ll discuss
is having a purpose.
それが果たす役割です
Now, when we travel on a literal road,
文字通りの道路についていえば
our plan usually is not to get on the road
旅をするとき 道路に行って
何もせずただずっと立ち止まっていたり
and just stand still (to become stationary)
行き交う人や車をただ眺めたりして
いるだけということは普通ありません
or watch other people or vehicles go by.
No, we’re there for a reason.
道路は何のためにありますか
The purpose of the road
is to enable movement
私たちは道路を使って
移動することができ
—to help us get from one place to another.
ある場所から別の場所に行けます
Well, in a similar sense,
being on Jehovah’s way of peace
それと同じように
エホバの平和の道があるので
allows you to move forward,
クリスチャンとして前進し
to make continual spiritual progress.
成長を続けていくことができます
And, of course, there are many ways
that we can make spiritual advancement.
エホバとの関係を深める方法は
いろいろあります
One important way
that all Christians can do so
私たち全てができる大切なことは
is by cultivating spiritual qualities.
クリスチャンとしての性質を
磨くことです
This is so pleasing to Jehovah.
エホバはそれを喜ばれます
Consider with me, for example,
例えば ガラテア 6:10では
こう勧められています
Galatians 6:10.
Notice what’s mentioned here
at Galatians chapter 6,
ガラテア 6:10をお読みします
verse 10.
そこにはこうあります
It says: “So, then, as long as we
have the opportunity,
「ですから 機会がある限り
全ての人に
“let us work what is good toward all,
特に同じ信仰を持つ兄弟姉妹に
but especially toward those
related to us in the faith.”
善いことを行いましょう」
それで クリスチャンとして成長する
1つの方法は
So one way to advance spiritually
is to look for ways
to do good things for others,
兄弟姉妹にも
クリスチャンでない人にも
both inside and outside the congregation.
善いことを行う機会を探すことです
This pandemic has afforded us
many opportunities to do this.
コロナ禍で これまでそのような
機会がたくさんありました
We’ve been able to call and check on others
電話をして様子を尋ねたり
必要な食料などを届けたりできます
and distribute food or supplies when needed.
And think of what our brothers
自然災害のたびに
ほかの人を助けるために
have done time and again to assist others
兄弟たちはたくさんのことを
行っています
during natural disasters.
So take a minute and think
about your local area.
皆さんの周りの人について
考えてみてください
どうすれば全ての人に
善いことを行えますか
How can you work what is good toward all?
Are there ones
that need assistance getting food
ちょっと買い物に行ってもらえると
助かるという人がいるでしょうか
or running errands?
Is there someone who could use
元気の出る励ましの言葉を
掛けてあげられる人が
a good word of encouragement
to cheer them up?
誰かいるでしょうか
Do we know individuals
who have lost loved ones in death
また 身近な人を亡くした人に
with whom we could share words of comfort
何か慰めの言葉を掛けたり
or maybe simply provide a listening ear?
話を聞いてあげたりすることが
できますか
You see, by displaying spiritual qualities
クリスチャンらしい性質を発揮して
親切や同情心を示し
—qualities such as kindness,
compassion, hospitality, generosity—
もてなし 気前よく与えるなら
you’re going to feel deeply rewarded
そのようにして本当に良かった
報われたと感じるでしょう
for doing these things.
And you’re pleasing Jehovah
エホバはそれを喜ばれます
because you will show that your purpose
命に至る道にいるのは
自分を救うためだけではなく
for being on the road to life
is not just to save yourself
他の人を助けるためでもあるからです
but to help others.
大切な役割です
Now, there was a third similarity
between being on a literal road
3つ目に考える文字通りの道と
命への道の共通点は
and being on the road to life.
In both cases,
どちらにもたどり着きたい
we have a destination
目的地があるということです
that we want to reach.
Traveling on a literal path
will eventually take you to your destination.
文字通りの道を進んでいくと
やがて目的地に着きます
And as a Witness of Jehovah,
エホバの証人として
この比喩的な道を進み
our journey, our walk,
on this figurative road
歩んでいくと
will lead us to our destination
やはり目的地に着きます
エホバとの平和な関係を
—the goal of enjoying
a peaceful friendship with God forever.
永遠に楽しめるようになるのです
Although we long for that time
in God’s new world,
神の新しい世界でそうなるのが
本当に待ち遠しいですが
even now we can experience
the blessings and inner peace
今でもエホバに仕える生き方から来る
that come from a life of service to Jehovah.
祝福と心の平和を味わえます
We now have the privilege
to speak with Sister Gloria Herd.
ここでグロリア・ハード姉妹を
ご紹介します
Sister Herd has been baptized
for over 70 years
ハード姉妹は70年以上前に
バプテスマを受け
and has enjoyed a rich spiritual life
in special full-time service
統治体のサミュエル・ハード兄弟と
共に特別全時間奉仕を行い
with her husband,
Brother Samuel Herd of the Governing Body.
クリスチャンとしての人生を
楽しんでこられました
Sister Herd, you’ve had
many rich spiritual blessings,
ハード姉妹 姉妹はたくさんの祝福を
味わってこられましたが
and we know that you’ve encountered
challenges along the way.
同時にいろいろな問題にも
直面してこられましたね
But as you’ve carried out
these assignments through the years,
これまで長い間
さまざまな割り当てを果たし
エホバの平和の道を歩む中で
walking in Jehovah’s way of peace,
心の平和を味わうのに
何が助けとなりましたか
how have you managed
to enjoy greater inner peace?
I’ve learned, Brother Turner,
that if Jehovah gives you an assignment,
エホバが割り当てを与える時は
それを果たすのに必要なものも
与えてくれると学びました
he will give you what you need to fulfill it.
We learned and really benefited
from the traveling overseers and their wives.
旅行する監督と奥さん姉妹が
大きな助けになりました
It was such a privilege to serve along
with these faithful brothers and sisters,
忠実な兄弟姉妹と共に働けたことは
喜びでしたし
and several of them had served me
and my family when I was very young.
小さい頃 家族でお世話に
なった方もいました
So to see their faithfulness,
to see their happiness,
兄弟姉妹が忠実で 幸福で 心の平和を
持っている様子も とても印象的でした
and to see that they really had inner peace
そうした兄弟姉妹たちに本当に教えられ
良い手本に倣いたいと思いました
really benefited me.
I learned from that,
and I wanted to follow their example.
そうした助けは本当に貴重ですね
ほかにもありますか
That help from others can be so valuable.
How else have you managed?
I’ve enjoyed inner peace too
from praying to Jehovah a lot.
エホバにたくさん祈ることによっても
心の平和を味わいました
Many times we had
very little money or no money,
お金がほとんど いえ全くないことも
よくありましたが
but we never missed a meal,
食事を欠かしたことも 集会や大会を
欠かしたこともありません
and we never missed any theocratic event.
We learned that having no money
お金がないことはエホバに仕える上で
問題にならないということを学びました
is not an obstacle to Jehovah.
エホバが祈りを聞いて答えてくださり
He heard our prayers, he answered them,
まるで天から祝福が降ってきたかの
ように感じることもありました
and it was as if the blessing
sometimes just fell out of heaven.
祈りには本当に力がありますね
Prayer can be so powerful.
Thank you for sharing that.
But now, how has walking
in Jehovah’s way of peace
エホバの平和の道を歩むことは ほかの
人との平和にどのように役立ちましたか
helped you to have peace with others?
I worked and lived with many sisters,
たくさんの姉妹と共に働き
生活しましたが
and they all had different personalities.
皆それぞれ個性がありました
So I learned that I had
to apply Romans 12:18,
「できる限りのことをして
どんな人とも平和な関係でいるように
しましょう」という
where it says:
“As far as it depends [upon me],
be peaceable with all men [and women].”
ローマ 12:18を当てはめるように
しました 平和を保つために
So I learned that I have to adjust
自分の方が人に合わせなければ
ならないことがあると学びました
my personality sometimes to keep peace.
This happened very often.
いろいろありましたが
例えばある火曜日の午前に
But one time, we moved in
with a sister on Tuesday morning,
宿舎の姉妹の家に着いた時
私が言ったことで
and something I said upset her very much.
姉妹を
とても怒らせてしまいました
She got very angry.
姉妹と1週間生活することになるので
Well, I decided not to pursue the issue
反論はしないことにしました
because I had to live with her for a week.
And I just decided
to let her see by my conduct
そして 姉妹が思っていたような
つもりで私が言ったのではないことを
that I could never have meant
what she thought.
行動で示すことにしました
日を追うごとにだんだんと
緊張は和らいでいきました
So as the week went by,
the days went by, the tension lessened.
And by Monday when we left,
we were the best of friends.
月曜日に出発する時には
姉妹は親友として
ぎゅっとハグしてくれました
And she gave me a big hug,
and nothing more was said about the subject.
もうあの話は出ませんでした
ハード姉妹 クリスチャンの性質を表し
Well, it sounds like you
handled that beautifully, Sister Herd.
Your spiritual qualities were evident.
良い仕方で対処されましたね
Well, finally, how has walking
in Jehovah’s way of peace
では エホバの平和の道を歩むことは
神との平和にどう役立ってきましたか
helped you have peace with God?
Well, when you see Jehovah act
エホバが自分のために何度も何度も
行動してくださっているのを見ると
on your behalf over and over and over again,
it makes you feel that you have his approval.
認めていただいていると感じます
Now that Sam and I are in our senior years,
主人も私も年を取りましたが
エホバが長年の目標だった
we feel He has given us
‘the desire of our heart’
ベテル奉仕という心の願いをかなえて
くださったことを感謝しています
by allowing us to serve at Bethel,
which had been our goal for many years.
And I know that as long as
I stay faithful to Jehovah,
エホバに忠実であり続ける限り
これからもずっと心の平和を
与えていただけます
he will continue to grant me inner peace.
And we have that confidence as well.
本当にそうですね
ハード姉妹 ありがとうございました
Thank you so much, Sister Herd.
励みとなる経験を
話してくださったことに
We deeply appreciate your comments
and your encouraging expressions.
心から感謝します
Well, let’s now address our final point.
では 最後の点を考えましょう
What can we do to continue walking
エホバの平和の道を歩み続けるために
どんなことができますか
in Jehovah’s way of peace?
Well, let’s go back
to our illustration of the road.
もう一度 道の例えで考えましょう
On a literal road,
travelers may need to make adjustments
文字通りの道を進む時
道路の状況や天候に応じて
in response to changing road conditions
何らかの調整をしなければ
ならないことがあります
or bad weather.
Similarly, as you go on walking
in the way of peace,
同じように 平和の道を歩み続ける中で
you will need to readjust your actions
and thinking from time to time.
時々自分の行動や考えを
調整する必要があります
Recently, a circuit overseer
shared an interesting point
ある巡回監督が考え方や態度について
regarding our thoughts
and attitudes on matters.
興味深いことを話してくれました
He said that they could either serve
兄弟によれば それは刑務所にもなれば
as a prison or a passport:
パスポートにもなります
a prison, in that our thoughts and actions
考え方や行動次第で制限されて
いるように感じるという意味で
can confine or restrict us
刑務所のようです
or a passport,
でもそれ次第で
in that they can take us where we need to be.
行くべき所に行けるので
パスポートのようです
Well, right now, we need to be
私たちは今 命に至る
この道にとどまることを
決意しなければなりません
and stay on this road to life.
So we want to make sure
that any needed adjustments are made
クリスチャンとしての進歩を
制限されたり 妨げられたりしないよう
考え方や行動で
in our thoughts and our actions
so that we’re not confined or restricted
少しでも調整が必要なところがあるなら
in making spiritual progress.
ぜひ調整したいと思います
Well, what might be some areas
では 調整が必要かもしれない
どんな分野があるでしょうか
that we’ll need to make adjustments?
Notice, please, Paul’s words
in 2 Corinthians chapter 13.
コリント第二 13章の
パウロの言葉に注目しましょう
And we’ll read 2 Corinthians 13:11.
コリント第二 13:11を
読みましょう
Paul says: “Finally, brothers,
「最後に 兄弟たち
“continue to rejoice, to be readjusted,
これからも喜び
正され 慰められ
“to be comforted, to think in agreement,
同じ考え方をし
平和に生活してください
“to live peaceably;
and the God of love
and of peace will be with you.”
そうすれば 愛と平和の神が
共にいてくださいます」
Did you notice three areas in this verse
このうち3つの点に注目して
where Paul states we can make adjustments?
どんな調整ができるか考えましょう
First, he says: “Continue to rejoice.”
1つ目として
「これからも喜び」とあります
We can lose our peace and joy
生活上の心配事で圧倒されてしまうと
if we become overwhelmed
by the anxieties of life.
平和と喜びを失いかねません
So in order to rejoice,
それで 喜ぶために
can you make it a goal to focus on things
悲しみではなく 喜びをもたらすことに
目を向けるようにすることができますか
that bring joy rather than sadness?
So if you’re not feeling well
or coping with chronic pain,
調子が悪かったり
いつも痛みと闘っているなら
you can focus on God’s promise
of when no one will say:
「私は病気だ」と言う人は
いなくなるという神の約束に
注意を向けましょう
“I am sick.”
If you’re facing opposition for your beliefs,
信仰ゆえに反対に直面しているなら
focus on the fact
that we’re part of a brotherhood
私たちを支え 祈ってくれている
兄弟姉妹がいることや
—a brotherhood that supports
and prays for us—
信仰を強く保つために必要なものが
and arrangements are in place
to keep us spiritually strong.
組織から与えられていることについて
考えてください
世界の出来事を見て
If you’re discouraged by world events,
you can rejoice in the fact
暗い気持ちになるとしても
将来に希望があるので喜べます
that you have a hope for the future,
and we know how this all ends.
私たちは知っています
We know that better times are ahead.
間もなく良い時代が来るのです
The point is, Don’t let negative thoughts
大切なのはネガティブな
考えにとらわれて
restrict or limit your progress.
進歩が妨げられないようにすることです
Instead, make the needed adjustments
そうではなく
必要な調整を行って前進し
so that you can move forward
and continue to rejoice.
これからも喜びましょう
Note another area for readjustment
that Paul mentions in verse 11.
11節でパウロが述べた
別の点に注意を向けましょう
There he says: “Continue . . .
「これからも⋯⋯同じ考え方を
し」とも述べました
to think in agreement.”
There were members of the congregation
1世紀のクリスチャン会衆には
back in the first century
that were promoting apostate ideas.
背教的な考えを
広めている人たちがいました
Others were introducing controversial ideas
聖書に反しないものの分裂をもたらす
考えを持ち込む人もいました
that were not directly unscriptural,
but they were divisive.
その結果として
This resulted in bickering
and arguments over words,
会衆内に言い争いや
言葉を巡る論争が生じ
really creating
a spiritually unhealthy atmosphere.
一致してエホバに仕えるのが
難しくなりました
Well, what’s going to help us
これからも同じ考え方をするのに
何が助けになるでしょうか
to continue to think in agreement?
Remember Paul’s words at 2 Timothy 2:23
テモテ第二 2:23には
こう書かれています
to “reject foolish and ignorant debates,
「愚かで無意味な議論を避けなさい
そうした議論は争いを生むからです」
knowing that they produce fights.”
Of course, we react strongly
when facing issues
もちろん エホバの道徳基準に
反することについては
that clearly violate Jehovah’s moral laws.
はっきりとした態度を取ります
But if no Scriptural principle
is being violated,
でも 聖書の原則に反しないのであれば
個人的な意見を押し付けないように
するのは大切なことです
we’re wise to abstain
from promoting our personal opinions.
We want to do all we can to avoid starting
会衆の平和を乱しかねない
不和を生じさせたり
or being drawn into disagreements
それに巻き込まれたりしないよう
that can disrupt the peace
of the congregation.
できる限りのことをしたいと思います
Now, back in verse 11,
コリントの聖句に戻って
調整できる3つ目の点として
a third area where we can make adjustments
「これからも⋯⋯平和に
生活してください」とあります
is to continue “to live peaceably.”
Did you notice
from the interview with our sisters
先ほどインタビューを受けた姉妹たちが
平和を脅かす問題に直面した時
what they both did when challenged,
どんなことをしたと言っていたか
覚えておられますか
when faced with a challenge
that threatened their peace?
They took the matter to Jehovah in prayer.
2人ともエホバに祈りました
They reflected on scriptures
found in God’s Word.
そして神の言葉をじっくり思い巡らし
And then they looked to see
how they could apply those verses
それから自分の状況に
どのようにその聖句を当てはめられるか
見極めました
in their particular situation.
It helped them to not only have inner peace
その結果 心の平和と共に
but peace with others as well.
他の人との平和も得ることができました
So let your spiritual qualities
shine through.
ぜひクリスチャンらしい性質を
発揮してください
Continue to work on keeping peace,
これからも平和を保つ努力をし
showing those qualities
of being loving and generous toward all,
全ての人に愛と親切を示しましょう
but especially with our close family members,
身近な家族に特にそうしてください
whether they are Witnesses or not.
クリスチャンであってもなくてもです
Well, we want to conclude
by reminding you baptism candidates
バプテスマ希望者の皆さん
今日が皆さんの歩みの中で
エホバとの関係において
that today marks a significant milestone
本当に重要な日であることを
忘れないようにしてください
in your journey
in your relationship with Jehovah.
So take the time to appreciate
今日この日が 自分にとって何を
意味するかじっくり考えてください
what this day means for you.
We’re so proud of all of you.
私たちもうれしいです
You will never regret
the decision you have made
皆さんはエホバに献身する
生き方を選んだことを
to dedicate your life to Jehovah.
決して後悔することはありません
But keep in mind that after today and beyond,
でも 忘れないでください
バプテスマを受けることは
the journey is not yet over.
旅の終わりではありません
それは始まりです
Really, it’s just the beginning.
So we encourage you
to do all you can
それで命の道に
とどまることができるよう
to stay on the road to life.
できる限りのことをしましょう
Keep in mind the points we considered today.
今日は大切なことを考えました
1つ目に エホバの平和の道を
歩むのを諦めないこと
First, do not give up
on walking in Jehovah’s way of peace.
Your life depends on it.
命が懸かっています
Allow Jehovah to guide your steps.
エホバに歩みを導いてもらいましょう
2つ目は 命に至る道の
境界内にとどまることです
Second, stay within the boundaries
on the road to life.
Remember, you’re walking with a purpose,
道には役割があり
and that will lead you to your destination
そこを進んでいくと目的地に着きます
—peaceful friendship with Jehovah forever.
ずっと続くエホバとの平和な関係です
3つ目に
And finally, keep making
any needed adjustments
考え 態度 行動に
必要な調整をしていくなら
in your thoughts, attitude, and actions
エホバとの平和 他の人との平和を
so that you can maintain peace
with Jehovah and peace with others.
得られます
If you continue to do these things,
こうしたことを行い続けるなら
not only will you have peace
平和を得られるだけでなく
コリント第二 13:11で
約束されているように
but as the last part
of 2 Corinthians 13:11 says:
“The God of love and of peace
「愛と平和の神が
共にいてくださいます」
will be with you.”
May you always remember that promise,
そのことをいつも覚えていてください
平和の道を進み続ける人に
which Jehovah makes to those
エホバがそう約束しているのです
who go on walking in the way of peace.
どうもありがとうございました
Thank you, Brother Turner.
Similar to last year,
去年と同じく
the arrangements for baptism
will vary in each location.
バプテスマの取り決めは
場所によって異なります
Each local congregation’s elders
have made suitable provisions
会衆の長老たちが 地元の状況に応じて
in accord with local circumstances
この後バプテスマ希望者が
バプテスマを受けられるよう
for candidates to be baptized
after the conclusion of this session.
ふさわしい取り決めを
設けていることでしょう
We thank Jehovah
for the timely spiritual food we enjoyed
今日も 大会でエホバが役立つ教えを
与えてくださったことに感謝できます
during this session of the convention.
Our next session will show us how to avoid
2日目の午後は どうすれば
平和を妨げるわなを避けられるか
common pitfalls to pursuing peace.
It will highlight specific activities
平和をつくる人が得意なことは
何かを学びます
that peacemakers excel at.
We will also enjoy part one
of the feature Bible drama.
楽しみにしていた
ドラマの第1部を見ることができます
But now, let’s sing together
the closing song for this session,
では ご一緒に結びの歌を歌いましょう
song number 54, “‘This Is the Way.’”
「これが道である」という主題の
54番です
After the song, you may have
your own concluding prayer.
歌の後 それぞれの場所で
祈りを捧げてください
That’s song number 54.
歌は54番です